<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A manifestation of truth ... writ in answer to a book which a nameless author hath written against the people called Quakers : wherein is contained divers untruths and hard speeches tending to beget jealousies and evil thoughts of them who are known to be harmless and innocent ... : also the truth of those things which they believe and practice ... is declared / by John Whitehead.</title>
            <author>Whitehead, John, 1630-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65902</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1979</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26356</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09436526</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09436526</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43103</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65902)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43103)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1320:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A manifestation of truth ... writ in answer to a book which a nameless author hath written against the people called Quakers : wherein is contained divers untruths and hard speeches tending to beget jealousies and evil thoughts of them who are known to be harmless and innocent ... : also the truth of those things which they believe and practice ... is declared / by John Whitehead.</title>
                  <author>Whitehead, John, 1630-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43103:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MANIFESTATION OF TRVTH</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Concerning the Scriptures, and concerning the Word, Light, and Spirit within.</item>
               <item>2. Concerning trial of Spirits.</item>
               <item>3. Concerning Perfection.</item>
               <item>4. Concerning Salvation by Chriſt.</item>
               <item>5. Concerning Swearing.</item>
               <item>6. Concerning the Worſhip of God, and why we ſeparate from thoſe that worſhip in Temples made with hands.</item>
               <item>7. Concerning Miniſters and Maintenance.</item>
               <item>8. Concerning womens ſpeaking in the Church.</item>
               <item>9. Concerning Superiours and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours, and the honour that is due from the one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wherein ſomething is ſaid concerning Title, Courteſies, and Salutation by the highway.</item>
            </list>
            <p>WRIT IN ANSVVER To a BOOK which a Nameleſs Author hath written againſt the People called QUAKERS WHEREIN</p>
            <p>Is contained divers Untruths and hard Speeches, tending to beget jealouſies and evil thoughts of them, (who are known to be Harmleſs and Innocent) in the Authors Tennants and Neighbours, to whom he hath ſent this Book, which is here detected, and the Innocency of Gods ſervants cleared: Alſo the Truth of thoſe things which they believe and practice in theſe particulars aforeſaid is declared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> John Whitehead, <hi>who hath no pleaſure in ſtirring up ſtrife and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention about things of his nature; And therefore hath laboured rather to manifeſt the Truth, to the unbiaſſed Reader, than particularly to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce his Adverſary, deſiring that he and thoſe to whom he directed his Book, may have a ſight of this, if peradventure it may be in inſtrumental to remove from them all prejudice, that they may receive the naked Truth, as it is in Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:43103:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friendly Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have lately received in manuſcript a ſmall Book, which in the fear of the Lord I have read over, and ſeriouſly pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, which I was the more induced to, becauſe I had ſome ground to ſuſpect, (if not to conclude) that it was writ by <hi>Lord Say,</hi> who hath been famous for the profeſſion that he hath made of Chriſtianity: And therefore I ſhould admire,<note place="margin">Iſa. 29.14.</note> but that I know the pleaſure of the Lord is to confound the wiſdom of the wiſe, and bring to nothing the underſtanding of the prudent, from whom he hides that which he reveals to babes, that no fleſh might glory in his ſight: I ſay, but that I know and do conſider theſe things, I ſhould admire, that he (who hath read the Scriptures,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.25.</note> and ſo long profeſſed Chriſt, who ſaid that men would ſay all manner of evil of his bleſſed and peculiar people) ſhould be ſo far degenerated, both from Chriſtian Charity and true Nobility,<note place="margin">Ch. 5.10</note> as to harbour ſo many evil thoughts and groundleſs jealouſies of an Innocent harmleſs people; and my ſoul mourns, that he is ſo far given up to believe lies, and report ſuch palpable untruths againſt us; amongſt which I ſhall only inſtance theſe few, as none of the leaſt, <hi>viz</hi> That <hi>George Fox</hi> deſired a Gentlewoman to wear a Bracelet for his ſake, and thereby enchanted her to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, from which <hi>George Fox</hi> hath approved himſelf innocent as a child, and ſo ſhall I ever look upon him, till the ſpreaders of that ſlander bring forth their Author: That <hi>James Nailor</hi> made himſelf, or ſaid of himſelf that he was Chriſt, is another lie; though it be true, that ſome fooliſh women (which both he and we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved) ſaid ſo of him; And it hath often been proved and print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſhame of the firſt raiſers of that ſlander, that he never ſaid of himſelf, that he was as holy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> juſt and good as God: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore till the contrary be made manifeſt by ſome known Author, we muſt conclude that another lie: A fourth is,</p>
            <p>That Jeſuites and Prieſts are known to mingle themſelves amongſt us, and be our Teachers and Inſtructers; which thing I know to be falſe; and the grievous ſufferings of divers of my dear friends for teſtifying againſt their bloody perſecuting principles, and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous worſhip, may ſufficiently evince that we mingle not with them, nor they with us; And my hearts deſire is, that <hi>Engliſh</hi> men might beware, leſt while they look for Jeſuites and Popiſh Prieſts amongſt us, they be not led by them themſelves into ſuch ſnares
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43103:2"/>as they cannot eaſily break; and till the parties be named which ſee one of our friends go with a rope about his middle to hang a Miniſter, I ſhall conclude that another lie; becauſe I know it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to our very nature and principle, who are born from above, which is to ſave mens lives and not to deſtroy; as alſo all whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and uncleanneſs is an abomination to us; therefore do we both warn and teſtifie againſt the practiſers of it, which is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to demonſtrate, that he who ſolicites to filthineſs, and ſhe who ſaid ſhe was commanded of the Father to go to bed to a man (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none of her husband) if any ſuch there were) are not of us, therefore do I conclude thoſe reports ſlanderous. Divers other hard ſpeeches and groundleſs ſuggeſtions I find, which I ſhall not particularize, being ſatisfied they are not grounded upon any juſt cauſe given by us either in doctrine or practice; alſo hoping that the Author may be ſenſible ſay this time (wherein truth is riſen above ſlanders) that he hath overſhot himſelf in writing ſuch grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous things againſt us, whom I am perſwaded he doth not ſully know; and therefore I cannot wonder if he do perſecute, which yet I will not poſitively affirm, though I do certainly know that his principle leads to it, which ſaith, that a Blaſphemer may juſtly be put to death in Goſpel times; though Chriſt Jeſus, who is far more excellent then <hi>Moſes,</hi> gave no ſuch command, but rather held forth the contrary in the whole courſe of his doctrine and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice:<note place="margin">Read Mat. 13.</note> But if he with whom I now deal have had his hand againſt any, which for conſcience ſake could not reſpect his perſon, ſo as to impriſon their perſons or ſpoil their goods for things done in obedience to the Light of Chriſt in their conſciences, though con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his judgement, that will be found in Gods day perſecut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their perſons, under the pretence of perſecting the Devil and their ſin, which narrow cover the moſt bloody perſecutors ever had; but howſoever,<note place="margin">Jer. 20.10.</note> this I ſay and do deſire that he may know it if he be yet alive, that he is at leaſt guilty of their ſin, who ſaid, Come let us ſmite him with the tongue, report ye, and we will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it; But ſurely, the Lord ſees how we are ſet as a mark for every one to ſhoot at,<note place="margin">Iſa. 25.8.</note> and I am perſwaded that when he hath fully tryed us, he will rowl away the reproach from us for ever; And their eyes that wait to ſee us ſlumble and fall into foul enormities (as divers profeſſors (but not profeſſors of the fame Life) have done) ſhall certainly fail; for hitherto hath the Lord helped us and bleſſed us, and made us to ſtand in the ſufficiency of his grace in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43103:3"/>the ſight of our enemies, and I know that his preſence is yet with us, and we are of him, and not of that Spirit that they were of at <hi>Munſter,</hi> who followed <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leydon</hi> and thought to build up <hi>Sion</hi> with blood and beat down its enemies with carnal weapons, for though they might pretend to be led by the Spirit within them, we know that that which led them into uproars, war and blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, was not the Spirit of Chriſt which leads us, for it teaches us to love our enemies and to ſave mens lives and not to deſtroy.</p>
            <p>And for the corrupt principles and practiſes of thoſe called Ranters, we have given teſtimony againſt them, which all that have heard and duly weighed in that Spirit that tries all things, can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that we are as far from them as light from darkneſs; but whereunto ſhall I liken the men of this generation? for when the Spirit of Chriſt doth ſo work in the hearts of any that they cannot run with the world into rioting and exceſs, then preſently they will call it Belzebub,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.25.</note> or the Devil transformed into an Angel of Light, as the Phariſees did unto Chriſt in the dayes of his fleſh; and if they called the Maſter of the houſe Belzebub, no wonder if it be more done to them of his houſhold. But as for ſelf-mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, voluntary humility, and will worſhip, whereof we are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, we know it avails not; but thoſe which do by the Spirit mortifie the deeds of the fleſh, ſhall finde comfort in ſo doing, and an humble heart,<note place="margin">Iſa. 57.15.</note> with a broken and contrite Spirit which doth fear God and tremble at his Word, however that be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached as one of the Devils tricks; yet ſuch a one God delights to teach and dwell in;<note place="margin">Ch. 66.2.</note> and we with whom his Tabernacle is, do not worſhip in our wills, but in Spirit and Truth; neither do we ſay that it is a perfect demonſtration of humility to caſt away band-ſtrings, lace and ribbonds, though we believe it a duty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent upon us to abſtain from wearing things ſuperfluous and unſerviceable; and alſo from all exceſs in meats and drinks, though we know the Kingdom of God ſtands not therein, yet we deſire to be found temperate and in modeſt apparel,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.9</note> according to the good example of the ancient Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>And further I do obſerve how the Author of that writing with which I now deal, hath often miſrepreſented our doctrines and practiſe, as further may appear by a ſerious view of his, and what follows, thereby I perceive he doth not rightly underſtand us, and I am perſwaded did never regularly try our Spirits, either by a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber hearing of our doctrines declared by our own mouths and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43103:3"/>pens, or by his own view of our practiſes, but hath heard and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved what evil and prejudiced men have maliciouſly printed and ſaid againſt us on purpoſe to ſlander and render us odious. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in anſwer to what is ſaid againſt us, I ſhall labour rather (for the ſtopping of ſlanders and to prevent miſconſtructions) to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Reader of the Truth of thoſe doctrines which we do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and practice, then particularly to traduce the Author with whom I have to deal, though in many things more I might ſhew wherein he hath wronged us and given unſound conſtructions both of Scripture and our doctrines and practices.</p>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <head>Concerning the Scriptures, and concerning the Word, Spirit, and Light within.</head>
               <p>Concerning the Scripture, I ſay we do not ſlight them nor caſt them off as a dead Letter, Paper and Ink, but own them which <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, Evangeliſts and Apoſtles did write or ſpeak forth as they were moved by the Spirit of God, (ſo far as they are free from falſe tranſcription and corrupt tranſlation) to be the very words and true ſayings of God, and therefore not to be ſlighted, but read, believed, and practiſed by every true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; but they that are unlearned of Chriſt,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.10.</note> whoſe hearts are not ſtabliſhed by the grace of God do pervert or wreſt the Scriptures out of their right place to their own deſtruction, not rightly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing betwixt the Law and Goſpel times, nor betwixt that which was aboliſhed for the unprofitableneſs thereof, and that which God hath eſtabliſhed for ever; and therefore we do direct all to that Word of God which was in the beginning before the Scriptures were written,<note place="margin">Read Joh. the firſt.</note> of which the Scriptures teſtifie that it is Life, and is the Light of men that ſhines in darkneſs, even in mens dark hearts, ſhewing the groſneſs and corruption of their hearts; I ſay, this Word which was and is God the Saviour of all them that believe, who ſearcheth all hearts and incomprehenſibly dwels in his Kingdom that is in man, and doth reprove man for his unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and evil deeds) we do direct all to wait to knovv this ingrafted Word and hearken to it,<note place="margin">Luke 17.20, 21.</note> that they may not be unlearned but all taught of the Lord that Spirit, vvhich holy men of God knevv and did believe in,<note place="margin">Jam. 1.21.</note> and vvas moved or led by, before the Scriptures vvere vvritten; that ſo by this Interpreter one of a thouſand peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may have the Scriptures opened, and feel the povver of God,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43103:4"/>and have faith in the povver and live in the life that the Primitive Chriſtians lived in;<note place="margin">Act. 26.17, 18.</note> and thus to direct people to the Word, Spirit, or Light of God vvithin, is none of the Devils vvork (as he ſaith) but the vvork of Chriſts ancient Miniſters; neither doth it make void the Scriptures,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 1 2, 3.</note> but eſtabliſheth them in their right place as a true Declaration: and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt vvho is that quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Spirit (vvhich doth enlighten every man that cometh into the vvorld) in his right place as the foundation which unto all generations ſtandeth ſure;<note place="margin">Joh. 1.9. 1 Cor. 3.9. 2 Tim. 2.19.</note> neither can our directing people to this foundation (Chriſt the Light vvhich enlightens their conſciences) have ſuch bad effects as to lay them open to all baſe luſts, error and deluſion, for all thoſe things are condemned vvith the Light, and they that believe and do ſuch things go from, and againſt the Light in their ovvn conſciences.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <head>Concerning the tryal of Spirits.</head>
               <p>I ſay the Apoſtle gave forth no ſuch command, as that we ſhould try the Spirit of God by the Scriptures, for it is moſt abſurd to try the ſuperior by the inferior; and no man can rightly underſtand the Scripture nor diſcern Spirits whether they be of God or no, but by the Light of the Spirit of God within,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14.</note> Therefore are they worthily reproved who preſume by ſtrength of reaſon, ſharpneſs of wit and humane learning, both to judge of the Scripture and of the Spirit of God and its movings in men,<note place="margin">Jer. 31.33</note> as the Scribes, Phariſees and chief Prieſts did, who in their pride and ſelf-wit ſate as Judges of the Law in the letter,<note place="margin">Iſa. 8.20. Heb. 10.16</note> and thereby condemned Chriſt the Prince of Life, and alſo his bleſſed Martyr <hi>Stephen,</hi> as blaſphemers that were not worthy to live; and this was the fruit of trying the Spirit by the Scripture when mans wiſdom ſate as Judge of both,<note place="margin">Note, That we own the Scriptures to be a rule, but not the onely rule whereby to cry Spirits.</note> which is rather to be judged by them both; and let ſuch as know no other rule whereby to try Spirits but the Scriptures, confeſs they are ignorant of the Law written in the heart, and of the teſtimony of Jeſus, which is the Spirit or Word of Propheſie that is near in the heart even the more ſure Word, ſurer then the words of the Prophets or Apoſtles, which may be wreſted; for it is a Light in a dark place (<hi>viz.</hi> the heart) to give man a true un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of their words; and his Law that is written there, is perfect and unalterable; and by this rule holy men of God tryed Spirits before the Scriptures were written, and ſo all the Spirits
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43103:4"/>that are gone out into the world may be tryed, and thoſe that are contrary to it are alſo contrary to the Scriptures rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and therefore under the judgement of both;<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19</note> but the Spirit of God judgeth all things, but ought to be judged of no man; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſad will be their accompt that call it the Devil, and its moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, his impulſes; for all ſins and blaſphemies againſt the ſon of man may be forgiven,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.31, 32</note> but the blaſphemy againſt the holy Spirit ſhall not be forgiven, neither in this world, nor in that to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <head>Concerning Perfection.</head>
               <p>We ſay firſt, that we have ſinned and God hath let us ſee it, and we have confeſſed it,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 1.7.</note> and he hath forgiven it through the blood of Chriſt which doth waſh and cleanſe us from it, and by his power we are kept from ſinning; yet do we not boaſt of perfection in our ſelves, becauſe by the grace of God we are what we are: howbeit we know that it is the Commandment of Chriſt that we ſhould be perfect even as our Heavenly Father is perfect;<note place="margin">Mat. 5 48</note> and therefore we are perſwaded it is not impoſſible for us to be ſo whilſt here in this life, for he is not ſuch an hard Maſter to command impoſſibilities:<note place="margin">Heb. 10.10; 14.</note> and moreover, by one offering he hath for ever perfected them that are ſanctified; and we are ſanctified through the offering of the body of Jeſus once for all, therefore perfected for ever: and this was, and is the very end for which he ſends forth his Miniſters,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.11, 12, 13</note> even to gather the Saints into the unity of the Faith, to a perfect man in the merſure, fulneſs and ſtature of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3 5, to 11.</note> who even for this purpoſe was manifeſt, to take away ſin and deſtroy the works of the Devil; but if any will yet ſay, that cannot be whilſt here in this life for, ſome ſin will remain in men whilſt on this ſide the grave, let them anſwer me theſe queſtions. 1. Whether they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that any ſhall enter in, to inherit Gods Kingdom? and if yea, then whether they believe that they ſhall enter into it with ſome ſin in them? and if nay, then in what time and place ſhall they be cleanſed, and their ſin perfectly done away, ſeeing they deny it to be poſſible whilſt in this life? but we affirm it, being perſwaded that there is no purgatory wherein to be cleanſed after death, and knowing that Chriſt Jeſus is able to ſave to the uttermoſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.25</note> they that come to God by him; ſo that thoſe that are born of God and abide in Chriſt, ſin not, neither can becauſe they are born of God, and his ſeed remains in them; contrary to which text no interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43103:5"/>of it, or argument can ſtand good; but herein are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God and the children of the Devil made manifeſt; he that doth righteouſneſs is of God, but he that ſinneth is of the Devil, who ſinneth from the beginning: and this doctrine doth not tend to Ranting, as they that underſtand it not, ſay; but to encourage people to wait to be cleanſed and kept by the mighty power of God from all unrighteouſneſs, which is all ſin, and preſs on to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in the Life of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <head>Concerning Salvation by Chriſt.</head>
               <p>We ſay and believe, that without the ſufferings and death of Chriſt at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> no man can be ſaved, juſtified or ſanctified, and therefore do they maliciouſly or (at leaſt) ignorantly ſlander us, who ſay we expect not to be ſaved by Chriſts ſufferings at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> but by Chriſts ſufferings in us; for ſuch words did never proceed from us, though we ſay, that it is not an hiſtorical know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and belief of what Chriſt ſaid and ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred years ago<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that can or doth ſave any man without feeling of his Spirit,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.10.</note> Power and Life made manifeſt within, to make them conformable to him in his death, and raiſe them together with him to live in the vertue of his life, by which life we as well as the ancient Chriſtians are ſaved,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.10</note> and we are juſtified, ſanctified in the Name and by the Spirit of our God which mightily work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in us, and all his works are perfect: and therefore I do diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh betwixt the righteouſneſs which is of faith,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.11</note> which the Spirit worketh, and the righteouſneſs which is of the Law performed by mans own ſtrength; for though the one be as filthy rags, yet ſo is not the other; therefore is he the enemy of all righteouſneſs that mingles them both together, and treads them under foot as dung and droſs; therefore let all that love their ſouls, love Chriſt the righteouſneſs of God and follow after him, that they may be made righteous, and have that boldneſs in the day of judgement which the ancient Chriſtians had, becauſe (ſaid they) as he is, ſo are we in this world.<note place="margin">1 Joh 4.17</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <head>Concerning Swearing. To ſwear at all in Goſpel times, is no part of Gods worſhip; therefore it is no deluſion but the truth that makes us refuſe to ſwear in any caſe.</head>
               <p>For though ſwearing was uſed in the time of deaths reign from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43103:5"/>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and that by ſome of Gods people; and not only ſo, but commanded in ſome particular caſes by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets in the time of the Law; yet a greater Prophet being raiſed, to whom they all gave witneſs and command that in all things he ſhould be heard, with this ſevere penalty, that every foul that would not hear him ſhould be cut off from his people;<note place="margin">Acts 3.22, 23, 24.</note> And ſeeing Chriſt Jeſus that Prophet which they ſaid God would raiſe, hath found that Covenant faulty in which oaths were uſed,<note place="margin">Mat. 5 34.</note> and by his own mouth expreſly hath commanded us not to ſwear at all; though in old time it was lawful and an honour to God to ſwear in ſome caſes, yet now it is not lawful, or an honour to God to ſwear in any caſe, becauſe Chriſt Jeſus the great Law-giver, in the New Teſtament hath by plain and expreſs precept wholly forbidden it, againſt which precept no argument, concluſion or interpretation, whether of Council, Synod or private man, is good; though grounded upon the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the words of the Prophets, or practice of Gods Servants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Saints or Angels, for their words and practiſes are to be reduced to an harmony with his, and not his to theirs, he being given to be head over all things to his Church, which is his body, the fulneſs of him that filleth all in all; and therefore cannot the example of Saints or Angels, and much leſs the practice of men in ſtrife, juſtifie us in the breach of his command, had we no other ground for our denyal to ſwear; but to ſwear at all is againſt the Law of the Spirit of Truth that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in us, and derogates from the glory of his verity who hath made our yea, yea, and our nay, nay, in all things; but the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> who writ to the twelve Tribes ſcattered abroad, as if he had foreſeen that, becauſe of former precepts and cuſtoms they would have ſtood to juſtifie ſome ſwearing contrary to Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, was very poſitive, and expreſly did forbid it; above or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all things, ſaith he, my brethren ſwear not,<note place="margin">Jam. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 12.</note> neither by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, nor by earth (Mark) nor any other oath, but let your yea be yea, and your nay, nay, leſt ye fall into condemnation; Therefore we cannot ſwear by heaven nor the things therein, nor by earth nor the things therein, nor by any other oath, though by ſuch Chriſtians as be in the Apoſtacy from the Spirit and Life of Chriſt, it be accounted lawful; for if we did ſwear at all, we ſhould juſtly fall with them into the ſame condemnation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:43103:6"/>
               <head>Concerning the worſhip of God, and why we ſeparate from them that worſhip in Temples made with hands.</head>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe we do thus believe and declare, that God is a Spirit and dwells not in Temples made with hands,<note place="margin">Acts 7.48. Chap. 17.24, 25.</note> neither is rightly worſhipped there, and therefore we cannot joyn with them in worſhip, that be erred from the Spirit and from the Truth,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.8, 9.</note> and do in their wills worſhip in vain, having their fear to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God taught by mens precepts, and their worſhip conſiſts not of Gods Ordinances, but in divers obſervations, inventions and traditions, which are not the Commandments of the Lord from heaven,<note place="margin">Read Iſ. 2.</note> but rather a loathing to his ſoul and a grief to his ſpirit, becauſe in matter and manner they are contrary to the Primitive Chriſtians worſhip; For firſt, they did not ſprinkle In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, and call that baptiſme into the Church, that we can finde in the Scripture, nor in Hiſtory, for near the firſt three hundred years; neither was it a part of their worſhip to ſing <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms in rime and meeter, as in theſe dayes men do, which are far enough from the condition that <hi>David</hi> was in when he gave forth the Pſalms; and beſides, the Miniſters that were allowed among the Primitive Chriſtians did not read Prayers for money, nor ſtudy Sermons to laſt an hour and preach them for money; neither did the Primitive Chriſtians love to have it ſo, as the titular Chriſtians now do; who by their diviſions, envying and perſecuting about worſhip do make it manifeſt, that they are neither in the ſame Spirit nor worſhip in the ſame manner as the Primitive Chriſtians did, and therefore we ſeparate from them which we have ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ground to do,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.17, 18. 2 Tim 3.5.</note> though they had the very form of godlineſs, which yet they have not, ſeeing they are out of the power which ſhould crucifie them to the world, and the world to them; and are conformed like to the world, and for the generality of them do live in ſenſual luſts, if not in open Prophaneneſs; but although we cannot for conſcience ſake joyn with them in their worſhip, becauſe we do in heart believe it is not right; yet do we not (as he ſaith)<note place="margin">Joh 21. to the 24.</note> caſt off all worſhip and Ordinances of God; for we are ſought out by the Father to worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth, where we have found aceeptance with God at what time ſoever, and whereſoever we have been gathered together to wait upon him, whether by day or in the evening, as the true Chriſtians were
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43103:6"/>when <hi>Paul</hi> continued his ſpeech till midnight; and ſometimes we meet in a believers houſe, upper-chamber, field or barn,<note place="margin">Acts 20.7, 8.</note> as the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Chriſtians did, who were gathered out of the world, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the Jews worldly Sanctuary, and Heathens Temples, and yet were not of thoſe that did creep into houſes, and ſeparate themſelves, ſenſual, not having the Spirit, no more then we are, though by ſuch as accuſed them and perſecuted them, we have all manner of evil ſaid againſt us falſly, and are perſecuted as they were, becauſe for conſcience ſake we cannot forſake the aſſembling of our ſelves together as the manner of ſome is, but muſt meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the Name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.25 Mat. 18.20</note> that we may enjoy his preſence, and comfort and edifie one another in love.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <head>Concerning Miniſters and maintenance.</head>
               <p>We do ſay, how ſhall they preach and declare unto us the minde of God, except they be choſen and ſent of God?<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 15.</note> and therefore we do deny to hear ſuch as run, and are not ſent of God, but for lucre and honours ſake take upon them to Preach and ſpeak of thoſe things which by wiſdom, humane learning,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.2, 3 Job 38.2.</note> and natural parts they can never underſtand, but do darken counſel by words without knowledge; for the generality of them ſay, that revelation is ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and that they have no viſion in theſe dayes; therefore we won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not that they and their people are ſo ignorant of God,<note place="margin">Mat. 11 27</note> 
                  <hi>for none knows the Father but the Son, and he to whom the Son reveals him;</hi> neither do we wonder why ſo many periſh for want of true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (though we greatly pity to ſee it ſo) for we know that when the Teachers have no viſion (as by their own confeſſion they have not) the people periſh;<note place="margin">Prov. 29.18.</note> therefore we dare not truſt our ſouls with them, though people that have itching ears do chuſe them for their Paſtors; or ſuch Biſhops as exerciſe Lordſhip and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over peoples conſciences, impoſe them upon us; for the Lord Jeſus Chriſt is the Biſhop of our ſouls,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.19. Jer. 3.15.</note> and he hath given us Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours according to his own heart, that feed us with knovvledge and underſtanding, and leads us to living ſprings, and a fold of reſt,<note place="margin">Mar. 10 8, 9, 10.</note> and them vve do dearly ovvn and eſteem for their vvorks ſake that be Chriſt true Miniſters vvhom he hath ſent, and doth furniſh, and enable by the gift of his Spirit, for the vvork of the Miniſtry, vvho freely vvithout money or price have received the vvord of recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation and do freely preach it, coveting no mans ſilver or his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43103:7"/>gold, nor his corn, not his hay, nor his wool, nor his Lamb, but do caſt their whole care upon the Lord that hath ſent them; and do plow in hope<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> plant in hope, and threſh in hope, that the ground may be broken up that hath brought forth briars and thorns, and the true ſeed grow to a blade, an ear and corn in the ear, and then be ſeparated from the chaff; and ſuch as theſe ſhall never be fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate of their hope, nor want neceſſary things pertaining to this life, though they know not to day what they ſhall have to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row;<note place="margin">chap. 6.25, 26, 27. 1 Cor. 4.11</note> I know that they that preach the Goſpel ſhall never want a livelihood: <hi>But he that hath ſent them will take care to provide them a morſel in due ſeaſon;</hi> and ſuch as theſe (though ſome of them have no more certain dwelling place then the ancient Miniſters of Chriſt had) are made manifeſt in our conſciences, and ſo far ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and owned as the Miniſters of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.9. Heb. 7.16.</note> But for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Prieſts that are made by mans will, and have the Law of a carnal commandement for to uphold their Miniſtry and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and claim tythes of mens increaſe, a thing not mentioned by the antient Chriſtians; and when for pure conſcience ſake (and not for any corrupt ends, as our manifold ſufferings may evince) we cannot uphold that Jewiſh cuſtom, and Antichriſtian practice which hath been introduced in the dark night of Popery, then do they ſue us to Law, caſt in priſon and make ſpoil of our goods, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily the trebble value of what they demanded, but ſometimes amounting to the trebble trebble value of what they ſaid was due; which hath brought ſuch a blot on them, as, ſhall never be wiped off, and manifeſts them to be ſuch as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid had hearts exerciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with covetous practices, and ſuch grievous wolves as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid ſhould come, not ſparing the flock; therefore we do turn from them to the chief Shepherd,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.14 Act. 20.29</note> who hath redeemed us from being a prey to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <head>Concerning womens ſpeaking.</head>
               <p>That Daughters did Propheſie in the Congregations of Gods antient people, is evident;<note place="margin">Num. 11.2 Judg. 4.4, 5, 6. Joel 2.28, 29.</note> for to <hi>Iſrael</hi> God ſpoke by, or in <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and again, he ſpoke in <hi>Deborah</hi> to <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> and judged them by the words of her mouth, who ſate under the Palm tree for many years in the dayes of <hi>Barack;</hi> and <hi>Joel</hi> ſaid, that vvhen God did pour forth his Spirit, Daughters ſhould Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, as vvell as Sons;<note place="margin">Acts 21.9.</note> and one man had four Daughters that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43103:7"/>vvere Propheteſſes in the Apoſtles dayes, and divers vvomen vvere helpers of the Apoſtles in the vvork of the Miniſtry, as is both evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the Acts of the Apoſtles, and in the Epiſtles,<note place="margin">Read Rom. 16. 1 Cor. 11.5 ch. 14.22.</note> vvhere <hi>Paul</hi> alſo gave rules how they ſhould Propheſie, ſaying, <hi>That every wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man praying or Propheſying with her head uncovered, diſhonoureth her head: and where ſhould the woman Propheſie if not in the Church,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame Apoſtle commendeth that gift above many for edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Church; and ſaith, that Propheſie ſerveth not for them that believe not but for them that believe: ſo that it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that although he did not permit a woman to ſpeak in the Church, nor uſurp Authority over the man, yet he did permit the Spirit of God to ſpeak in vvomen, as vve do; for vve dare not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid it, leſt in ſo doing vve ſhould quench the Spirit vvhich they have the Promiſe of, as vvell as men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="doctrine">
               <head>Concerning Superiors and Inferiors, and the honour that is due from the one to the other: Alſo concerning Titles, Curteſie and Salutation by the way.</head>
               <p>In the beginning God did create all Nations of one blood to dwell upon the face of the whole Earth,<note place="margin">Acts 17.26</note> that they might glorifie his Name and live innocently in love one to another, but ſince the ſeed of the Serpent was received in mans heart, that naturally inclines him to pride, violence, and all other foul inormities: we are perſwaded that by Gods Ordinance ſome have a ſuperiority given them for the puniſhment of evil doers, and a praiſe to them that do well: As firſt, the Husband over the Wife. 2. The Parents over the children, the King over his Subjects, and the Rulers over the people, in their ſeveral Countries and liberties: alſo Maſters over their ſervants, and Miſtreſſes over their handmaids, and to theſe Superiors we are perſwaded by the Lord that there is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour due from inferiours: and in his Light we do ſee and know that it conſiſts not in vain Ceremonies wherein there is no ſervice to God or man, ſuch as uncovering the head, and bowing the knee: And therefore the examples of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> though good men, who bowed to <hi>Eſau,</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> to the <hi>Hevites</hi> a Heathen Nation, will not vvarrant us to bovv dovvn and vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip creatures againſt our conſciences, no more then their going in to their handmaids vvill vvarrant us to do the like: neither doth due honour conſiſt in vain complements, vvhich for the moſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43103:8"/>part are frivilous, fained and hypocritical, as, your ſervant Sir, I go Sir, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but in diligent and ſpeedy obedience to all juſt commands of Superiors, and in patient ſuffering under thoſe that are unjuſt, doth due honour conſiſt, for thoſe children do moſt honour their Parents, and thoſe Subjects their Prince, which are of good beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, temperate, ſober, wiſe, and humble, and do readily obey all their juſt commands, and patiently ſuffer chaſtiſement for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to obey that which is unjuſt; and this honour which is due from all Inferiors to Superiors, we do not at all teach any to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and therefore we can with confidence appeal to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of our very enemies and accuſers, that we do deſign to le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel nothing but ſin, wherein we are juſtified by the Lord, <hi>who will bring down the loftineſs of man,<note place="margin">Iſa. 2.11.</note> and bow the haughtineſs of his ſpirit, and exalt himſelf alone, as in the beginning, for he is worthy,</hi> becauſe he alone is the Lord; and therefore we cannot call any man the Lord beſides him,<note place="margin">1 Cor 8 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>6.</note> though we know in the world there is Lords many, and one of them we can call a Lord, but not the Lord, nor my Lord, becauſe God is the Lord, and there is none our Lord beſides him; and in like manner, we can call ſome Ladies as the antient Chriſtians did, yet not any elect Lady, but ſuch whoſe election we know, and why ſhould we call any my Lady, as he urges, unleſs by marriage union we have intereſt in them? And for ſuch as do any way demonſtrate to us that they are of a Noble and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſpirit, we ſhall not ſtick to call them Noble or honourable, as <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>Feſtus</hi> and others; but we ſee they are moſt degenerate from true Nobility and Chriſtian ſaith (and ſo leaſt deſerve it) which do ſo eagerly ſeek honour one of another,<note place="margin">Joh 5.44.</note> for to ſuch Chriſt ſaid, <hi>how can ye believe?</hi> rendring that as the reaſon of their unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief. And further, a King we can call by that title, and a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by that title, and thoſe that are our Maſters according to the fleſh by that title, and every one in their place by ſuch titles as are neither falſe, flattering, nor blaſphemous; but ſuch titles as are ſo, we cannot give to any,<note place="margin">Job 32<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21, 22.</note> for in ſo doing God would ſoon take us away. And for curteouſneſs to all, both to Superiors and to Equals, where is the man or woman among all our neighbours that have been converſant with us, that can juſtly accuſe us, and ſhew wherein we have not been curteous and amiable to them? unleſs they count it diſcurteſie to be reproved for evil, or not to have their perſons worſhipped, and adored as God, with uncover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the head, and bowing the knee, which is uſual when we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43103:8"/>to him in prayer; and if withholding that from men be eſteemed diſcurteſie, let them ſhew where God commanded it, or the antient Chriſtians gave it,<note place="margin">Heſter 3.5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6.</note> ſeeing <hi>Mordica</hi> denyed to give it (when required by a King) to <hi>Hamnan</hi> a perſon of great place, though thereby he did not only endanger his own life, but the life of all the Jews throughout the Provinces of <hi>Babylon.</hi> And further, if any do judge us not curteous for ſpeaking to them in that lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage which God and nature hath appointed for diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt ſingular and plural numbers, <hi>viz.</hi> Thou to a ſingle perſon, whether Superior or Inferior, and You to many; then let them come forth and ſhew the contrary to be a curteſie commanded, or commended by God or any of his Saints. And for not uſing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other vain cuſtoms and manners of the Nation in which we live, I know we are accuſed of diſcurteſie and unmannerlineſs, as for not uſing the drunkards cuſtom and manner, in drinking one to another, and pledging thoſe that drink to us, and for not uſing the ignorant peoples cuſtom and manner, in ſaying god even and god-morrow when we meet them, and other things wherein peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will not be held guiltleſs for taking Gods Name in vain, and uſing ſuch words as corrupt good manners,<note place="margin">Ex. 20.7.</note> and therefore we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be conformable to them, though for it we ſuffer reproach; and ſure if the Author of that writing with whom I now deal, had met ſome of Chriſts antient Diſciples, he would have ſaid they had gone by men like a Hog or a Cow (as he ſaith we do) when they were obedient to Chriſts command, who ſaid, <hi>ſalute no man by the high-way;</hi> and the Prophet ſaid, <hi>if any ſalute thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 10.4. 2 King. 4.29.</note> 
                  <hi>anſwer them not again.</hi> But in all other things wherein we may do any ſervice to God or our neighbours, where is the man that can ſay we refuſe, or are diſcurteous, or unneighbourly? and from whom have we withholden, either rents, debts, or other cuſtoms (as he accuſeth us) which in righteous reaſon and conſcience is due? but ſure our blameleſs converſation in theſe things may by this time have ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the evil ſurmizings and gainſayings of our adverſaries, and therefore I ſhall commit our cauſe to the Lord, who I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded will yet more and more plead it, and clear the innocency of thoſe that love him, by the riſing of his light which is a faithful witneſs in all conſciences to which we deſire more and more to be made manifeſt; And therefore we deſire that all ſober people may take heed of receiving falſe informations againſt us, whereby both they and we may be wronged, but rather firſt hear what we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43103:9"/>and hold for, and then judge of it and us, according to the Light of the Spirit which God gives them, and according to the Scriptures of Truth; and if by true tryal they finde us hold forth or practice that which is contrary to either, let them avoid it,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.2.</note> for on no mans conſcience would we impoſe any thing which he cannot freely receive, no more then we would be impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for it is our principle to do unto all men even as we would be done unto.</p>
               <closer>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Writ the</hi> 24th. <hi>day of the ſecond Month,</hi> 1662.</date>
               </closer>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:43103:9"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
